Soviet Union Islam Subject Files, Inclusive: 1954-2000, undated, Bulk: 1965-1975, 1977-1989, undated
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Soviet Union Islam Subject Files
Inclusive: 1954-2000, undated, Bulk: 1965-1975, 1977-1989, undated
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
17
Keston Institute, 1969 -
4 A4 document boxes
The Soviet Union Islam Subject Files contain a variety of materials on Islam and persecution of Muslim believers.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
Keston received documents dating from 1954-2000 concerning the political and religious climate in the Soviet Islam community The Muslim communities in the Northern Caucasus’ and Central Asia inhabited lands generally viewed as the last remnants of the Mongol Empire. After the Russian empire conquered the Siberian Khanate and its tributaries at the end of the 17th century, it turned toward the last frontier, the Northern Caucasus and Central Asia. Beginning in the 19th century, Imperial Russia conducted an aggressive campaign to annex the lands surrounding the Black Sea and the Caspian Sea. After several decades of fierce fighting, mass genocide and forced migrations of Muslim communities in the affected areas a brief, uneasy peace transcended on the region.
In the early 1920’s, the Bolsheviks and the victorious Red Army sought to reconquer the Northern Caucasus and Central Asia. The area had gained autonomy during the chaos of the Civil War (1917-1922). By the late 1920’s, the area was incorporated into a conglomerate of Soviet Social Republics (SSR’s). During the Great Patriotic War (1941-1945), many men from the SSR’s were drafted into the Soviet Army. Meanwhile, Joseph Stalin distrusted the loyalty of the ethnic groups in the Northern Caucasus and the Crimea. He initiated mass deportation of numerous ethnic groups, including Chechens, Crimean Tatars, and Meskhetian Turks and placed them in harsh conditions in Central Asia.
The files from the collection begin in 1954, shortly after Joseph Stalin’s death in March 1953. The following leader of the Soviet Union, Nikita Khrushchev, sought to undo many of Stalin’s reactionary policies in the Caucuses and Central Asia. He focused on increasing party control and rebuilding infrastructure in the area. Khrushchev faced the problem of Islam as both a religion and a national identity. He was also forced to deal with increasing concern over the Muslim birthrate, which far succeeded that of the Great Russian. Statisticians predicted that by the year 2000, the Muslim people would constitute over a quarter of the Soviet population. Khrushchev conducted atheist campaigns and forbade traditional Muslim practices, including the use of kalym or bride payment, the elimination of blood feuds, and traditional burial practices. He also ordered more aggressive policies, such as closing mosques, making holy sites into atheist museums, and making it illegal to possess a Koran.
However, the Soviets could not totally deny the presence or importance of Islam. Through “official” Islam, or state-controlled religion, Soviet ideology was spread using Islamic religious boards and hosting international conferences on Islam. Religious boards, which were established as governing bodies during the Great Patriotic War, controlled four distinct regions. Leadership of these regions was centered in Baku, Ufa, Alma-Ata, and Dushanbe. Only through approval of boards could official copies of the Koran be published, and new mosques established.
In the 1960’s and 1970’s, the Soviet Union hoped to capitalize on a wave of Pan-Islamism and Pan-Arabism prevalent in the Middle East and Northern Africa. The country hoped to assert Soviet influence by correlating these “isms” as achievable through Communist ideology. The Soviet Union touted its role as the fifth largest Islamic country in the world. Strategically referencing this position, the country attempted to insert itself into the Arab and Islamic worlds by hosting international conferences on Islam. The first conferences were held in the 1970’s and intermittently throughout the next decade.
The two most notable conferences met in Tashkent (1980) and Baku (1986). 1980 was a perilous year for Soviet propaganda in Muslim communities. Soviet officials expressed increasing concerned over the new revolutionary government in Iran, which had taken control after the Shah was disposed in 1979. Specifically, Soviets were leery that unrest would stir Muslim populations in the Soviet Republics on Iran’s border. Simultaneously, the Soviet Union faced a public relations problem in the Islamic international community after its invasion of Afghanistan. However, most Islamic countries boycotted the Tashkent Conference, which was meant to eliminate concerns over Soviet intentions in Afghanistan and its SSR’s. The 1986 Baku Conference, labeled “Muslims in the Fight for Peace,” fared slightly better.
To counter negative perceptions, Soviet policy toward Islam dramatically shifted in the 1980’s. Old mosques were restored, and a limited number of Korans and other Islamic literature was published. By the 1980’s, atheist agitators were still present in the Northern Caucasus and Central Asia, but official Soviet policy no longer sponsored reeducation drives. To improve its image, the USSR formed the International Department of Muslim Organizations of the USSR in 1984. The new department head, Mufti Schams-ud-Din Babakhum, was directed to show the international community that Communist Soviet Union tolerated religion and atheism did not oppose the principles of Islam.
When Mikhail Gorbachev took power in 1990, he tried to improve the standard of living in Central Asia by conducting an aggressive anti-corruption campaign. He directly linked the corruption to Islam to the failure of atheism to take hold in Central Asia. By 1991, relaxed Soviet policies toward Muslims and their general indifference toward atheism allowed Islamic religious practices to gain some autonomy. However, before Gorbachev could initiate new atheistic campaigns, the Soviet Union collapsed. The final documents in the collection show Islam in the aftermath of that collapse. The papers and pictures reveal an active Muslim community adherent to the practices of Islam, which had remained actively present in the previous decades despites Soviet persecution.
Scope and Content
Islam General Subject Files consist of newspaper clippings, typescripts, background reports, broadcasts, and bibliographic references.
Materials range from 1954-2002. The collection pertains primarily to the general progression of Islam in the Soviet Union. Files particularly focus on Islam as both a religion and a national identity. The practices of Islam in Central Asia and the Northern Caucuses are explored. These practices include circumcision, bride payments, burial ceremonies, and pilgrimages. These activities were viewed as symptoms of religious fervor which were out of line with official Soviet atheistic policies. Included in the general files are the expressed opinions and policies of anti-Islamic Communist party leaders and Soviet backed leaders in the Muslim community. Foreign opinions on the state of Islam in the Soviet Union can also be found in this collection.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received the Islamic materials in folders organized by specific categories as well as unprocessed. The materials have been arranged thematically and chronologically. Currently, the Soviet Union Islamic Subject Files are arranged in one series: I. General.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 17.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Abduldzhemil)', Mustafa, 1943-; Bobokhonov, Shamsuddin.; Dzhemilev, Reshat.
Subjects (Organizations)
Dukhovnoe upravlenie musul)'man Rossiĭskoĭ Federat͡sii.; Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.; Sovet muftiev Rossii.
Places
Soviet Union -- Ethnic relations.
Subjects
Islam -- Russia (Federation); Islam -- Soviet Union -- History.; Islam -- Soviet Union.; Muslims -- Asia, Central.; Muslims -- Caucasus.; Muslims -- Russia (Federation); Muslims -- Soviet Union -- History.; Religion and state -- Soviet Union.; Religious minorities -- Soviet Union.; Socialism and Islam -- Soviet Union.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Samizdat.
- General, 1954-2000, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains files related to general Islam in the Soviet Union. They include fluctuating Soviet attitudes toward religion, atheist education attempts, and general persecution of Islam. These documents relate to the policies of “official” Islam, which was state ordained, and the unofficial Islam that was practiced illegally. This series is in good condition.
  - Islam. General (1 of 12), 1954-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Islam. General (2 of 12), 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Islam. General (3 of 12), 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Islam. General (4 of 12), 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Islam. General (5 of 12), 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Islam. General (6 of 12), 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Islam. General (7 of 12), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Islam. General (8 of 12), 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Islam. General (9 of 12), 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Islam. General (10 of 12), 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Islam. General (11 of 12), 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Islam. General (12 of 12), 1992-2002, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - History, 1976-1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Pre-Revolution History, 1977-1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Soviet Period History, 1976-1994, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Individuals, 1975-1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mosque Administration, 1979-1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mosques, 1977-1979, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Central Spiritual Administration of Muslims of Russia, 1994, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Church-State Relations, 1967-1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Opening of Mosques, 1979-1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Registration of Mosques, 1979, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Oppressive Practices-Persecution, 1962-1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Harassment, 1971-1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Trials, 1974-1987 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Imprisonments, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Closure of Mosques, 1973-1981 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - State Expropriation, Desecration, or Demolition of Mosques and Sacred Cities, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Maltreatment of Believers in the Army, 1981, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Attacks in Media, 1973-1988 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Confiscation of Literature, Property, 1976-1983 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Religious Life, 1956-2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Festivals and Anniversaries, 1974-2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Rituals, 1978-1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Modernization, 1975-1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Haji-Pilgrimages, 1974-1988, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Life of Saints and Holy Men, 1983, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Conversion to Islam, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Mosque Life, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Defections from Faith. Secularization, 1966-1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Official Muslim Publications, 1979-1987 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Revival, 1981-1992, undrafted (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Religious Minority. Sufi, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Clergy. Priesthood, 1980-1997 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Individual Clergy, 1977-1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - International Relations, 1979-1994 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Western Reactions, 1979-1987 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Delegations from SU Visit Abroad, 1979-1987, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Religious Activities Not Approved by State, 1980-1987, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Rites. Ceremonies, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Protests, 1981-1988 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Defection-Emigration on Religious Grounds, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Samizdat, 1980-1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Commendation of Atheist Work, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Atheism in Education, 1981-1987 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Theology, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Religion and Science, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Philosophy, 1976-1981 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Islam and Intelligentsia, 1972-1976 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Schisms: Muridism: Imam Shamil, 1975-1992 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Statistics: Muslim Population and Numbers, 1976-1991 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Relations with Fellow Believers, 1976-1987 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Ecumenical Relations, 1976-1994 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Religion and National Identity, 1974-1989 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Involvement in Secular Affairs/Politics, 1977-1987 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Pronouncements on Secular Affairs, 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Contacts with Secular Organizations, Conferences, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Religious and Secular Political Movements, 1983-1995 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Peace Activities, 1976-1986, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Art. Architecture. Literature. Music, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Muslim Architecture, 1974-1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Literature, 1979-1992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Women, 1970-1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Children and Youth, 1973-1993 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Sociology of Family, 1959-1985 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Sociological Surveys, 1980-1994 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Visual Material, 1976-1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Muslims in Russia after Collapse of the Soviet Union. General, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Muslims in Russia after Collapse of the Soviet Union. Articles in Russian Press, 1996-1997, 1999, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Muslims in Russia after Collapse of the Soviet Union. Articles in Foreign Press, 1999, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Muslims in Russia after Collapse of the Soviet Union. Western Scholars Papers, 1996, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Muslims in Russia after Collapse of the Soviet Union. Roshchin, Mikhail. Manuscripts on Islam, 1999, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Muslims in Russia after Collapse of the Soviet Union. Institute of Central Asia Development, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Muslims in Russia after Collapse of the Soviet Union. International Conference "Islam - Religion of Peace", 1999 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Muslims in Russia after Collapse of the Soviet Union. Central and Regional Muslim Organizations, 1996-1998, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Muslims in Russia after Collapse of the Soviet Union. Proofs of Articles on Islam for RSS, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 17)